Guide to the William D. Wittliff Papers
The Wittliff Collections
- Screenwriting, 1973-1995
  - The Terrible Teague Bunch, 1975
    - Rough draft, September 23, 1975 (Box 303, Folder 5)
    - First draft, September 30, 1975 (Box 303, Folder 6)
    - First draft, September 1975 (Box 304, Folder 1-2)
  - Whirligig, 1976
    - Rough draft (Box 304, Folder 3)
    - Incomplete first draft (Box 304, Folder 4-6)
    - First draft (Box 304, Folder 7-8)
    - Polish of first complete draft (Box 305, Folder 1)
    - Scraps and fragments (Box 305, Folder 2-3)
    - Screenplay, 1976 (Box 305, Folder 4)
    - Reader's report (Box 305, Folder 5)
  - Red Headed Stranger, 1979-1988
    Final shooting script has original drawing by Wittliff and is autographed by Wittliff and Willie Nelson. Produced by Nelson and Wittliff. Directed by Wittliff. Script Supervisor Cate Hardman Roach. Film was edited in Wittliff's offices by Eric A. Williams and Stephen Purvis. Slides removed from original sleeves and put in archival sleeves. Marked original sleeves are in front of re-sleeved slides.
    - Scripts, 1975-1988
      - March 1, 1979 (Box 306, Folder 1)
      - March 8, 1979 (Box 306, Folder 2)
      - March 12, 1979 (Box 306, Folder 3)
      - Revised, May 1983 (Box 306, Folder 4)
      - April 23, 1984 (Box 306, Folder 5-7)
      - 111 pages (Box 307, Folder 1)
      - Step sheet (Box 307, Folder 2)
      - All revisions through, April 22, 1985 (Box 307, Folder 3)
      - Final shooting script, April 22, 1985 (Box 307, Folder 4)
      - Lined script, April 23, 1984 / September 16, 1988 (Box 307, Folder 5-6)
    - Production, 1985, undated
      - Story boards (Box 307, Folder 7-8)
      - Story boards (Box 308, Folder 1-6)
      - Story boards (Box 309, Folder 1-2)
      - Shooting schedule (Box 309, Folder 3)
      - Continuity Polaroids (Box 309, Folder 4-5)
      - Script Supervisor's notes and script (Box 309, Folder 6)
      - Continuity Script, Cate Hardman-Roach (Box 310, Folder 1)
      - Lined Script, 1985 (Box 310, Folder 2-3)
    - Post Production, undated
      - Code book (Box 310, Folder 4-5)
      - Sound notes & Cue Sheets (Box 310, Folder 6)
      - Editing log (Box 310, Folder 7-8)
      - Editing log (Box 311, Folder 1-2)
      - Film and tape (Box 311, Folder 3)
      - Publicity slides (Box 311, Folder 4-6)
      - Publicity slides (Box 312, Folder 1-6)
      - Publicity slides (Box 313, Folder 1-3)
      - Publicity photos and posters (Box 313, Folder 4)
      - Congratulations (Box 313, Folder 5)
  - The Mask of Aztlan, 1983-1985
    "This one got stuck between thinking and feeling. The best stuff (the old men, the feathered airplane, the Mask itself) come from cutting the subconscious loose. Much of the rest of the story is contrivance--that is to say, thought out. The two didn't mix." Bill Wittliff, February 24, 1989
    - Partial draft, January 3, 1983 (Box 314, Folder 1-2)
    - Draft, November 15, 1983 (Box 314, Folder 3-4)
    - 3rd draft, September 10, 1984 - January 3, 1985 (Box 314, Folder 5-9)
    - Rewrite, January 4-17, 1985 (Box 315, Folder 1)
    - January 17, 1985 (Box 315, Folder 2)
    - Polish, February 11 - 12, 1985 (Box 315, Folder 3-6)
  - Country, 1984-1987
    Written and co-produced by Wittliff. Starred Jessica Lange and Sam Shepard. Wittliff began as director but was replaced by Richard Pearce. 1985, Lange won Academy Award nomination. The film received the Christopher Award. Kelly Asbury drew story boards for Wittliff when he was director. Publicity contains reviews, congratulations, studio press kit, publicity junket which began in New York because movie opened the 1984 New York Film festival, final report of the screening program, report of gross receipts and distribution costs.
    - Storyboards (Box 316, Folder 1-7)
    - Storyboards (Box 317, Folder 1)
    - Previews, June - August 1984 (Box 317, Folder 2)
    - Press kit (Box 317, Folder 3)
    - New York Film Festival (Box 317, Folder 4)
    - Screening program final report (Box 317, Folder 5-7)
    - Reviews, September 1984 - January 1985 (Box 318, Folder 1-6)
    - Congratulations, September - December 1984 (Box 318, Folder 7)
    - Earnings Statements, 1985-1987 (Box 318, Folder 8)
    - Awards, January 1985 (Box 318, Folder 9)
  - The Cowboy Way, 1986-1993
    This started as a rewrite of Pistoleers--"My first couple of drafts were set in New York City--then Crocodile Dundee came out and the studio asked me to reset the story in Washington, D. C. to avoid comparison. Against my better judgment I agreed to give it a try and the whole thing (meaning the writing) went downhill after that." Bill Wittliff, February 16, 1989. Includes notes by Wittliff's assistant at the time, Connie Todd.
    - Pistoleers by Rob Thompson, undated (Box 319, Folder 1)
    - Pistoleros, first rough draft, May 9, 1986 (Box 319, Folder 2-4)
    - Draft, July 21 - September 10, 1986 (Box 319, Folder 5)
    - Polish of rough draft, September 11 - 15, 1986 (Box 319, Folder 6-7)
    - First draft, September 17, 1986 (Box 319, Folder 8-9)
    - Second draft, October 7 - 29, 1986 (Box 320, Folder 1-4)
    - Rewrite, February 24 - April 1, 1987 (Box 320, Folder 5-7)
    - Rewrite, May 4 - 18, 1987 (Box 320, Folder 8)
    - Rewrite, May 4 - 18, 1987 (Box 321, Folder 1-3)
    - Rewrite by Nick Castle, July 22, 1987 (Box 321, Folder 4)
    - Rewrite, September 28 - November 1, 1987 (Box 321, Folder 5-8)
    - Draft, November 2, 1987 (Box 321, Folder 9)
    - Draft, November 2, 1987 (Box 322, Folder 1)
    - Alternate plot piece, not used, undated (Box 322, Folder 2)
    - Rewrite of second draft, January 1990 (Box 322, Folder 3-4)
    - Rewrite, June 4, 1990 (Box 322, Folder 5-6)
    - Second draft, June 21, 1990 (Box 322, Folder 7)
    - Second draft, June 24 - 17, 1990 (Box 322, Folder 8-9)
    - Rewrite of second draft, July 20 - 27, 1990 (Box 323, Folder 1-2)
    - Polish of rewrite, July 28 - 31, 1990 (Box 323, Folder 3)
    - Polish, August 2, 1990 (Box 323, Folder 4)
    - Polish/rewrite of Aug 2, 1990 draft, January 27 - February 2, 1993 (Box 323, Folder 5-6)
    - Rewrite, February 11, 1993 (Box 323, Folder 7)
    - Rewrite, February 20, 1993 (Box 324, Folder 1)
    - Polish of rewrite, Feb 21, 1993 (Box 324, Folder 2-4)
    - Revised draft, June 17, 1993 (Box 324, Folder 5)
    - Rewrite of new draft, July 22 - 26, 1993 (Box 324, Folder 6)
    - Further rewrite, July 28, 1993 (Box 324, Folder 7)
    - Further rewrite, July 28, 1993 (Box 325, Folder 1)
    - Polish of rewrite, July 29, 1993 (Box 325, Folder 2-3)
    - Incomplete, undated (Box 325, Folder 4)
    - Draft by Nick Castle, November 29, 1989 (Box 325, Folder 5-6)
    - Draft by Nick Castle, December 12, 1989 (Box 325, Folder 7-8)
    - Production forms and dailies, undated (Box 325, Folder 9)
  - Venganza (Mexico Story), unproduced, 1989
    - Notes, February 13 - March 8, 1989 (Box 326, Folder 1)
    - First rough draft, March 20 - April 7, 1989 (Box 326, Folder 2-3)
    - Rewrite, April 10 - May 18, 1989 (Box 326, Folder 4-6)
    - Notes, partial rewrite of first draft, July 5, 1989 (Box 326, Folder 7)
    - Draft and additional corrected pages, August 9, 1989 (Box 326, Folder 8)
    - Draft, August 9, 1989 (Box 327, Folder 1-2)
  - In the Cathedral of the Wolves (unproduced), 1991-1992
    - Wolf Song by Jeanne Rosenberg, December 17, 1991 (Box 327, Folder 3-4)
    - Wolf Story rewrite by Wittliff, partial rough, March 7, 1992 (Box 327, Folder 5-6)
    - In the Cathedral of the Wolves first draft, April 18 - May 17, 1992 (Box 327, Folder 7)
    - First draft, May 17, 1992 (Box 328, Folder 1)
    - Notes by Connie Todd and rewrites, May 18-29, 1992 (Box 328, Folder 2)
    - Rewrite polish, June 1, 1992 (Box 328, Folder 3-5)
  - Ned Blessing (1991 Pilot), 1991-1992
    - Chapter 1: Tors Buckner
      - Drafts, January - July, 1991 (Box 329, Folder 1-11)
      - Polish and revisions, July - September, 1991 (Box 330, Folder 1-4)
      - Autographed script, undated (Box 330, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 2: Cornelius Bryant
      - Drafts and revisions, June - November, 1991 (Box 330, Folder 6-10)
    - Chapter 3: Out of the fire (began as Chapter 2)
      - Rough and first drafts, April 1991 (Box 330, Folder 11-12)
      - Final drafts, polish, and rewrites, April - November, 1991 (Box 331, Folder 1-7)
    - Chapter 4: Pie Wentworth
      - Drafts and revisions by Wittliff and Gary Cartwright, May - June, 1991 (Box 331, Folder 8-12)
      - Polished drafts, June - November, 1991 (Box 332, Folder 1-3)
    - Chapter 5: Oscar Wilde by Stephen Harrigan
      - Various drafts and rewrites, June - December, 1991 (Box 332, Folder 4-8)
    - Chapter 6: A Woman in Need
      - Drafts, December 1991 (Box 332, Folder 9-11)
    - Production
      - Notes, phone messages correspondence, October 1990 - November 1991 (Box 332, Folder 12)
      - Notes, phone messages, corresponden, December 1991 - October 1992 (Box 333, Folder 1)
      - Contracts, April - May, 1991 (Box 333, Folder 2)
      - Budget, April - June, 1991 (Box 333, Folder 3-5)
      - Director, March - October, 1991 (Box 333, Folder 6)
      - Casting, March - June, 1991 (Box 333, Folder 7)
      - Casting, June - October, 1991 (Box 334, Folder 1-2)
      - Staffing, undated (Box 334, Folder 3)
      - Story Boards by Mark Bristol, undated (Box 334, Folder 4-7)
      - Contact list, undated (Box 334, Folder 8)
      - Wardrobe, undated (Box 335, Folder 1)
      - Props, undated (Box 335, Folder 2)
      - Location, undated (Box 335, Folder 3)
      - Art Department Files, undated (Box 335, Folder 4-9)
        Description
        Art department files have location photos, snaps of props, set designs, research articles, set building plans, newspaper mockups.
      - Art Department Files, undated (Box 336, Folder 1-4)
      - Stationery, undated (Box 336, Folder 5)
      - Production Staff Memos, undated (Box 336, Folder 6)
      - Censorship, June - September, 1991 (Box 337, Folder 1)
      - Shooting schedule, January - September, 1991 (Box 337, Folder 2)
      - One line schedule, January - September, 1991 (Box 337, Folder 3)
      - Day Out of Days, September 1991 (Box 337, Folder 4)
      - Movement List, July - September ,1991 (Box 337, Folder 5)
      - Call Sheet, October 6-23, 1991 (Box 337, Folder 6)
      - Photographs by Bill Wittliff, undated (Box 337, Folder 7)
      - Lined Script, Script Supervisor Pam Fuller, undated (Box 337, Folder 8-9)
      - Daily Script Notes, September - October, 1991 (Box 337, Folder 10)
      - Dailies, undated (Box 337, Folder 11)
      - Postproduction, October 1991 (Box 337, Folder 12)
      - Titles, June 1990 - December 1991 (Box 337, Folder 13)
      - Music, January 1991 - April 1992 (Box 337, Folder 14)
      - Ratings, January - April, 1992 (Box 338, Folder 1)
      - Publicity, December 1991 - April 1992 (Box 338, Folder 2)
      - Clippings, January 1991 - April 1992 (Box 338, Folder 3)
      - Thank yous and Congratulations, 1990-1992 (Box 338, Folder 4-5)
      - Awards, Spur Western Writers Award, 1992 (Box 338, Folder 6)
  - Ned Blessing (1993 Series)
    6 part series, five of which aired August 1993 on CBS-TV.
    - Eli Cutter Promotional Material (basis for the series) (Box 339, Folder 1)
    - Plum Creek, Part I
      - Rough drafts, July - August, 1992 (Box 339, Folder 1-2)
      - Rough drafts and polish, August - October 1992 (Box 340, Folder 1-11)
      - Revisions and blue pages, October 1992 - March 1992 (Box 341, Folder 1-6)
      - Shooting script, signed by cast and crew (Box 341, Folder 7)
    - Ghost Story
      - Various drafts, October - November 1992 (Box 341, Folder 8-10)
      - Connie Todd notes, rewrites, and blue revisions, November 1992 - March 1993 (Box 342, Folder 1-4)
    - Smink Brothers
      - Various drafts, December 1992 - April 1993 (Box 342, Folder 5-10)
    - Oscar Wilde by Stephen Harrigan
      - Various drafts and rewrites, December 1991 - April 1993 (Box 343, Folder 1-6)
    - The Hooded Man
      - Various drafts, February - April 1993 (Box 343, Folder 7-9)
      - First draft and revisions, April 1993 (Box 344, Folder 1-2)
    - Production
      - Memos, 1993 (Box 344, Folder 3)
      - Entertainment Industries Council resource encyclopedia, undated (Box 344, Folder 4)
        Entertainment industry notebook gives suggestions on the media presentation of various social issues such as alcoholism, seat belts, tobacco, etc. Props file has drawings of gear by Brad Johnson. Continuity photos have photos from 1991 pilot mixed in.
      - Budget, 1992-1993 (Box 344, Folder 5-6)
      - Cost reports, April - May, 1993 (Box 344, Folder 7-8)
      - Budget, May - June, 1993 (Box 345, Folder 1)
      - Cost reports, June 1993 (Box 345, Folder 2)
      - Budget, 1994 (Box 345, Folder 3)
      - Production Staffing, September 1991 - May 1993 (Box 345, Folder 4)
      - Casting, October 1992 - April 1993 (Box 345, Folder 5)
      - Videotape of Rob Campbell screen test, undated (Box 345, Folder 6)
      - Cast and Crew list, February - May 1993 (Box 345, Folder 7)
      - Story Boards by Mark Bristol, March 3, 1993 (Box 345, Folder 8)
      - Censorship, November 1992 - April 1993 (Box 345, Folder 9)
      - Set & Location photos, undated (Box 345, Folder 10)
      - Set & Location photos, undated (Box 346, Folder 1-2)
      - Set & Location scrapbook, undated (Box 346, Folder 3)
      - Makeup & costume, undated (Box 346, Folder 4)
      - Props, undated (Box 346, Folder 5)
      - Continuity Polaroids, undated (Box 346, Folder 6)
      - Continuity Polaroids, undated (Box 347, Folder 1-4)
      - Day out of days, March - April, 1993 (Box 347, Folder 5)
      - One-line schedules, March 15 - April 14, 1993 (Box 347, Folder 6)
      - Shooting schedule, January - March 25, 1993 (Box 347, Folder 7)
      - Shooting schedule, March 29 - May, 1993 (Box 348, Folder 1)
      - Movement List, undated (Box 348, Folder 2)
      - Call sheet, undated (Box 348, Folder 3)
      - Photographs taken by Wittliff, undated (Box 348, Folder 4)
      - Script supervisor lined script, undated (Box 348, Folder 5-18)
      - Script supervisor lined script, undated (Box 349, Folder 1-2)
      - Dailies log, undated (Box 349, Folder 3)
      - Post production budget, undated (Box 349, Folder 4)
      - Editing, March - July, 1993 (Box 349, Folder 5)
      - ADR, undated (Box 349, Folder 6)
      - Music, January - June, 1993 (Box 349, Folder 7)
      - Titles, undated (Box 349, Folder 8)
      - Distribution, March 1993 (Box 349, Folder 9)
      - Publicity, April - August, 1993 (Box 349, Folder 10)
      - Ratings, August - September, 1993 (Box 349, Folder 11)
      - Clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 350, Folder 1)
      - Magazines, July - September, 1993 (Box 350, Folder 2)
      - Congratulations and Thank yous, September 1992 - September 1993 (Box 350, Folder 3-5)
      - Awards, 1993-1994 (Box 350, Folder 6)
  - Legends of the Fall, 1990-1993; 1994
    - Notes, step sheet, 1990-1993 (Box 351, Folder 1)
    - Notes, tape from Zwick, 1990-1993 (Box 351, Folder 2)
    - Book, underlined, undated (Box 351, Folder 3)
    - Partial typescript by Ed Zwick, undated (Box 351, Folder 4)
    - Partial rough draft of episodes, July 6 - October 5, 1990 (Box 351, Folder 5)
    - First draft, October 21 - November 18, 1990 (Box 351, Folder 6-8)
    - Rewrite, November 24 - December 18, 1990 (Box 351, Folder 9)
    - Rewrite, polish, November 24 - December 18, 1990 (Box 352, Folder 1-5)
    - Rewrite, March 25 - April 3, 1991 (Box 352, Folder 6)
    - Polish of second draft, April 5, 1991 (Box 353, Folder 1-3)
    - Rewrite of April 5 draft, January 6 - 14, 1992 (Box 353, Folder 4)
    - Rewrite of Jan 14 draft, January 15 - 22, 1992 (Box 353, Folder 5-6)
    - Final draft with additions by Ed Zwick, January 22, 1992 (Box 354, Folder 1)
    - Revised by Susan Shilliday, February 8, 1993 (Box 354, Folder 2)
    - Revised by Susan Shilliday, April 19, 1993 (Box 354, Folder 3)
    - Revised by Susan Shilliday with blue pages, May 8, 1993 (Box 354, Folder 4)
    - Arbitration of credits, undated (Box 354, Folder 5)
    - January 22, 1992 (Box 354, Folder 6)
    - February 5, 1992 (Box 354, Folder 7)
    - March 16 - July 6, 1993 (Box 354, Folder 8)
- Filmmaking, 1983-1994
  - Sundance Institute, 1983-1992
    The Sundance Institute for Film and Television was founded by Robert Redford to foster emerging talents, often found outside the mainstream of the traditional entertainment industry. For six years during the 1980s, Bill Wittliff served on the Board of Trustees for the Institute, working in particular on the Selection Committee. He also donated his time as a writer's mentor during the June Workshop at Sundance Resort near Provo, Utah and at the Writer's Workshop held during the January Sundance Film Festival.
    - Letters, minutes, 1983-1984 (Box 355, Folder 1-4)
    - Production Advisory Committee Meeting, October 1984 (Box 355, Folder 5-8)
    - Programs, reports, 1985 (Box 356, Folder 1-2)
    - 84 Charlie, Patrick Duncan, undated (Box 356, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, reports, 1985 (Box 356, Folder 4-5)
    - Ain't that America by Frank Pierson, August 2, 1985 (Box 356, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1986 (Box 356, Folder 7)
    - Milk and Honey by Trevor Rhone & Glen Salzman, May 1986 (Box 357, Folder 1)
    - Reports, minutes and programs, 1986 (Box 357, Folder 2-5)
    - End of the Line by Jay Russell & John Wohlbruck, October 1, 1985 (Box 357, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1987 (Box 357, Folder 7)
    - Reports, minutes, 1987 (Box 358, Folder 1-6)
    - Italian American Reconciliation by John Patrick Shanley, undated (Box 358, Folder 7)
    - Reports, 1987 (Box 358, Folder 8)
    - Reports, Programs, 1987-1989 (Box 359, Folder 1-6)
    - Reports, statements, minutes, 1990 (Box 360, Folder 1-4)
    - Screenwriters and their Craft videotapes, 1990 (Box 360, Folder 5)
    - Program, letter, 1992 (Box 360, Folder 6)
  - Scripts from other writers, 1980s-1990s
    - David Maraniss, Donald Howard (Box 360, Folder 7)
    - Winnetou by Karl May (Box 360, Folder 8-9)
  - Filmmaking-General Files, 1983-1994
    - Iwerks promotional package (Box 361, Folder 1)
    - Ed Sharpe interview of Wittliff (Box 361, Folder 2-3)